Guide to the Issachar Cozzens Portfolio Print Collection 1800-[1865] PR 145
New-York Historical Society
Issachar Cozzens portfolio print collection
1800-[1865]
New-York Historical Society
Cozzens, Issachar, 1780-1865
PR 145
0.3 Linear feet (72 prints)
Collection of early nineteenth century natural history and miscellaneous prints collected by Issachar Cozzens.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 1866.
Arrangement
Print numbers were assigned by Cozzens
Biographical Note
Issachar Cozzens Jr. (1780-1865) was a New York distiller. He also had an interest in natural history and political history, and collected maps, manuscripts, and prints relating to these fields. It is thought that he obtained a sizeable number of Dr. Samuel L. Mitchill's papers from the cellar of the Almshouse in City Hall Park before it was destroyed by fire in 1854. Mitchill (1764-1831) was a noted professor of Natural History and print collector. Cozzens pasted these prints and maps, along with others of alternate provenance, in a large scrapbook.
Scope and Contents
The Issachar Cozzens Portfolio Print Collection spans the period from 1860 to ca. 1865 and primarily contains early prints related to natural history and New York topics. Cozzens assembled a scrapbook with engravings, certificates, caricatures, lithographs, drawings, and maps of the New York area, natural history specimens, buildings, portraits, and landmarks. Many of the prints in the scrapbook bear the initials "SLM," as Samuel L. Mitchill owned many of these prints before Cozzens acquired them. Cozzens pasted most of the documents onto a pink paper in the scrapbook and added his handwritten notes.
The collection includes early lithography by Arthur J. Stansbury, some of the first known lithographs to have been produced in New York City. Other lithographs are by Imbert and included engravings are by Alexander Anderson, Peter Maverick, and Francis Davignon. An early engraving by Alexander Anderson, a "Wheel of Fortune," is the only known impression of this print. Many natural history pages include drawings of fish, several made by Cozzens himself. The collection includes a copy of the Declaration of Independence and several learning charts, including a toxicological table, illustrations of the eye, and an outline of the Linnean system of classification. Portraits and geographical prints round out the collection.
After its acquisition by the New-York Historical Society, Cozzens' scrapbook was disbound and its components were distributed among several different departments. The following container list includes prints held by the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections. A transcription of Cozzens' original list of prints (the original is held by the Society's Manuscript Department), with call numbers for those items now located in the General Library Collections, can be consulted in the repository.
For more in-depth information about the collection, its provenance, and some of its prints, see the article "Portfolio of a Curious Mind: The Issachar Cozzens Collection" by Jenny Gotwals in the New-York Journal of American History, Volume 65, Number 4, Fall 2004, pages 48-57.
Biology -- Classification -- Charts, diagrams, etc.; Natural history -- Pictorial works.; Toxicology -- Charts, diagrams, etc.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Charts; Drawings (visual works); Engravings (prints); Lithographs.; Prints (visual works).; Anderson, Alexander, 1775-1870; D'Avignon, Francis, 1813-; Imbert, Anthony, 1794 or 1795-1834; Maverick, Peter, 1780-1831; Mitchill, Samuel L. (Samuel Latham), 1764-1831; Stansbury, Arthur J. (Arthur Joseph), 1781-1865
- Masonic Certificate by L. Jackson, engraved by R. C. Bruen, undated (Folder 1, Item 1)
- Lithograph of Samuel L. Mitchell by Imbert, undated (Folder 1, Item 4.1)
- Copy plate print of Archibald Bruce, professor of minerology, drawn by Brown, engraved by Hoagland, undated (Folder 1, Item 4.2)
- Lithographic print of John Endicott, first governor of Massachusetts, drawn by F. Davignon, published by George and William Endicott, 1843 (Folder 1, Item 5.1)
- Certificate of the Society of Agriculture Arts and Manufacturing, undated (Folder 1, Item 5.3)
- Certificate of the Royal Humane Society of London, 1814 (Folder 1, Item 5.4)
- Diploma from American Institute for 'the best geological cabinet', 1843 (Folder 1, Item 6.2)
- Caricature of the sailing of the U.S. Ship the Peacock on a voyage of discovery to the South Pole under the Command of Commodore Wilkes by H.R. Robinson, [1838] (Folder 1, Item 8)
- Wheel of Fortune, a caricature by Alexander Anderson, 1800 (Folder 1, Item 9)
- Richard Wilcox's Patent tubular Boiler and Economical Engine for Propelling Vessels by Steam or other fluids, undated (Folder 1, Item 15)
- A plan of the great picture of the Crucifixion exhibited in New York about 1842 -- Key to H. Sebrons' Diorama of the Crucifixion (Folder 1, Item 33)
- A Toxicological Table, shewing the symptoms, treatment, and methods of detecting the various mineral, vegetable, and animal poisons. By Hay Stevinson, 1826 (Folder 1, Item 42)
- Outline of the Linnean System, arranged for the use of the Students of Rutgers Medical College, by Dr. David Hosack, printed by J. Seymour., [1825-1827] (Folder 1, Item 44)
- Illustrations of the Eye: Original and Selected, by W.C. Wallace, Oculist., 1840 (Folder 1, Item 45)
- Comparative View of the Heights of the principal mountains in the world, drawn by H. Morse, published by R. P. and C. Williams., 1820 (Folder 1, Item 48)
- Drawing of a fossil skull supposed to be a gigantic bear from a cave in Sandwich, England., 1819 (Folder 1, Item 49)
- "Duria Antiquior," lithograph of a restoration of antidiluvial animals, drawn by H. T. de la Beche, lithographed by G. Scharf, 1839 (Folder 1, Item 50)
- "Coal-Mine of Treuil, near St. Etienne," lithograph, drawn by Jacques Milbert, printed by Barnet and Doolittle, 1822 (Folder 1, Item 51)
- Six curious ink blotches made by Dr. Taylor and sent to Dr. Mitchell as curiosities, undated (Folder 1, Item 52)
- The boiling fountain of Iceland, hand colored lithograph, undated (Folder 1, Folder 53)
- Geological profile extending from the Atlantic to lake Erie, engraved by Rawdon, Clark and Co., 1822-1823 (Folder 1, Item 56)
- Geological profile showing the western edge of lake Erie, engraved by Rawdon, Clark and Co., 1822-1823 (Folder 1, Item 57)
- Advertisement for Benjamin Trembley's building services with a lithograph by Imbert, undated (Folder 1, Item 59)
- American Zoological Museum: Two noble living lions Pompey and Bonaparte now exhibiting in W. J. Hanington's Museum corner of Broadway and Canal St., lithograph by A. D. Hollosy, 1831 (Folder 1, Item 60)
- Six pairs of beggars, lithograph by A. J. Stansbury, 1821-1822 (Folder 1, Item 61.1)
- Two cherries on leafy branch, lithograph by A. J. Stansbury, 1821-1822 (Folder 1, Item 61.2)
- Restaurant near Sybil's Cave, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3)
- Fishing houses near the Elysian Fields, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3)
- Farmhouse on Hoboken Road, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3)
- Cottage in the Elysian Fields, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3)
- Indian Huts near Hoboken, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3)
- Sybil's Cave on the Hudson, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3)
- West Point Foundery and Boring mill, engraved by P. Maverick, Durand and Co., undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3A)
- Map of Madison's Cave, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3B)
- Sketch of rock archway, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3D)
- Redwood Library of Newport, RI, drawn by James Stevens, engraved by W.D. Terry, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3E)
- Colossal statue, undated (Folder 1, Item 61.3F)
- Colored seashells, 1826 (Folder 1, Item 62)
- Nineteen drawings of Natural History, twelve by Cozzens, undated (Folder 2, Item 63)
- Eighteen drawings of the fishes of New York, sixteen by Cozzens, undated (Folder 2, Item 64)
- Twenty-seven drawings of fishes, nineteen drawn by Cozzens, undated (Folder 2, Item 65)
- Twenty-nine drawings of fishes, twenty drawn by Cozzens, undated (Folder 2, Item 66)
- Twenty-three drawings of whales, some by Cozzens, undated (Folder 2, Item 67)
- Seven outlines of fishes, undated (Folder 2, Item 68)
- Fourteen plates and drawings of specimens in Natural History, undated (Folder 2, Item 69)
- Forty-eight colored drawings of shells, undated (Folder 2, Item 70)
- A Tammany Certificate, drawn by Charles Buxton, engraved by George Graham, handcolored, 1804 (Folder 3, Item 71)
- Another View of Old Stone Mill, [before 1825] (Folder 3, Item 72.2)
- Plan of John Braggs patent bridge, lithograph, undated (Folder 3, Item 72.4)
- Plate of the Medical College of South Carolina, engraved by J. Wood, [before 1828] (Folder 3, Item 72.5)
- Plate of the Asylum for the Insane, engraved by Rawdon, Clark and Co. for A. T. Goodrich, 1826 (Folder 3, Item 72.6)
- Connecticut Retreat for the Insane at Hartford, drawn and engraved by E. Gallaudet, 1827 (Folder 3, Item 72.7)
- View of the New-York Hospital, drawn by John R. Murray, engraved by Leney, undated (Folder 3, Item 72.8)
- Elevation of the New York State Prison, drawn by Joseph Mangin engraved by Gilbert Fox, undated (Folder 3, Item 72.9)
- The Ground Plan of State Prison at Greenwich New York, drawn by Joseph Mangin, engraved by Gilbert Fox, undated (Folder 3, Item 72.10)
- Image of Genisa, undated (Folder 3, Item 73.3)
- Image of Vishnu, undated (Folder 3, Item 73.4)
- The Indian Mummy, undated (Folder 3, Item 73.6)
- View of Scudder's American Museum, at the right is a view of the old jail now alter into the Hall of Records, [before 1830] (Folder 3, Item 73.8)
- View of Marthing House, Rockland County, undated (Folder 3, Item 73.9)
- Caricature of Dr. Mitchell while he is arranging his apparatus for a Lecture, his flunky is just entering the door while the Dr. has sat down an artificial globe -- watercolor, undated (Folder 3, Item 73.10)
- Anatomical figure of the Heart, Larynx, etc., undated (Folder 3, Item 73.11)
- Plans for the pauper and lunatic Asylum on Blackwell's Island, Alexander J. Davis, architect, undated (Folder 3, Item 74.1)
- Conflagration of the U.S. Steam Frigate Missouri, Gibralter, Aug. 27, 1843, as she appeared on the morning of the 27th, drawn by George B. Souder, lithographed by Thayer & Co., Boston. (Folder 3, Item 75.1)
- Conflagration of the U.S. Steam Frigate Missouri, Gibralter, Aug. 27, 1843, at the moment the order was given to abandon ship, drawn by George B. Souder, lithographed by Thayer & Co., Boston. (Folder 3, Item 75.2)
- Phrenological Tree and Chart, exhibiting the Classification and Location of the Mental Facilities, 1840 (Folder 3, Item 78)
- Antidiluvian monster skeleton, engraved by M. Navarro, undated (Folder 3, Item 87)
- Antiquities from Asia brought to New-York in Jan. 1817, by Capt. Henry Austin, and now at Dr. Mitchill's. drawn by C.H. Smith, engraved by A. Anderson for Henry Meigs, Esq. (Folder 3, Item [unnumbered])
- Portrait of James Harper, Esq., mayor of New York, drawn and lithographed by F. Davignon, 1844 (Folder 3, Item [unnumbered])
- Copy of Declaration of Independence, engraved by Peter Maverick, published by Benjamin Owen Taylor, 1818 (Folder 3, Item [unnumbered])
- Eulogium Sacred to the Memory of the Illustrious George Washington, Columbia's Great and Successful Son, engraved by Peter Maverick, designed, written, and published by Benjamin Owen Taylor, 1815 (Folder 3, Item [unnumbered])
- Launch of the Steam Frigate Fulton the First, at New York, 29th, Octr, 1814, drawn by J. J. Barralet, engraved under and published by B. Tanner, Philadelphia., 1815 (Folder 3, Item [unnumbered])
- [Banknote Specimen], printed by Durand & Wright, 1823 (Folder 3, Item [unnumbered])